okay thank you very much uh thank you everyone for
joining us today to the magnets i'm anita dijiara
and together with the magnet scene we want to
welcome you all for the first talk of the 2022
um so we will have uh about 20 to 25 minutes
presentation you're invited to keep your
microphone muted um and then after that we'll
have some time for question and answers you can
text you can you can write in the text chat but i
can ring that the your question out loud for you
and and then there's going to be a time for
informal catch up at the end which is not
going to be recorded and for today i'm really i'm
really excited uh to welcome here andy biggin from
university of liverpool who will be talking on
potential sources of variability and stability
in the poly magnetic field thank you
andy please share your screen thank you
okay hopefully that's nice and clear that's fine
thank you andy okay so thanks very much for the
uh the introduction thanks to all the
organizers for for inviting me and laying
on this this great uh seminars uh series um
so i'm going to be uh well the aim of this
talk is to bring you up to date with um some
stuff that's been going on at the liverpool um
uh some of the stuff that's been
going on the liverpool group um
starting off with with dipole moment
then if there's time we'll move on to the
paleocecular variation and the theme
running through this talk will be um using
uh dying the outputs of dynamo simulations
and comparing those two to magnetic fields
it's paleomagnetic records okay and
that's only possible through the help of
a whole bunch of collaborators
some of whom i've named here
so um i like to categorize uh causes of
paleomagnetic variability into sort of three
um different processes so on the shortest time
scale i've got what i'm referring to is non-linear
geodynamo processes so this is things like secular
variation and then when that gets a little bit out
of hand we call that an excursion and then when
that gets really out of hand the field collapses
and then when it grows back it's got the opposite
polarity we call that um a reversal um but i guess
the key thing about this uh cause of paleomic
variability is that it's the geodynamo doing its
own thing it doesn't need forcing from the outside
at all on a slightly longer time scale overlapping
then we have uh potential uh forcing for mantle
convection so the mantle is the ultimate heatsink
for the outer core and it uh as such it's
the ultimate provider of convective power
uh for driving um the dynamo and therefore
things like uh changes in the magnitude and
the pattern of the of the commental boundary
uh heat flux um may be expected to affect the
the geodynamo and the magnetic field that results
from it so that could be you know any true polar
wonder will rotate that pattern um globally in the
reference frame of the geodynamo and then you've
got changes in uh subduction flux uh resulting
from the things related to wilson cycles and
supercontinental cycles and so on and then on
even longer time scale have what we've referred
to as core mental um evolution so this is things
like the secular cooling of the the entire entire
planet and at some point the uh core grew so cold
that is able to mutate um solid inner core at its
center and that was a game changer for the the
dynamo as we'll get to and then there's various
uh exotic processes that have been um hypothesized
in recent years and sort of things like exsolution
of silicates within within the core that would
also cause very long time scale uh changes um
so i think it's fair to say that that my research
interests for a long time uh and those of others
as well i've worked with have been associated with
trying to use paleomagnetism magnetism as a tool
for getting at uh understanding deep earth and
its evolution so really modes uh processes two
and three on here um but you've got to be very
careful i want to recognize the the danger uh for
misidentification of which one of these processes
you're actually seeing in in paleomagnetic
records so i'll illustrate that by just talking
quickly about um some dynamo simulation output so
this is a simulation a very special one because
out of the 154 simulations we have on catalog
at liverpool and this is the very best at meeting
the criteria of spraying a tile 2019 qpm criteria
for showing similar magnetic field behavior in
a statistical sense um to that observed from
paleomagnetic records over the last uh 10 million
years okay so there are five criteria uh matching
um referenced here so two of them relate to what
we call model g um for paleocecular variation
where we plot the um bgp angular dispersions
essentially at angular standard deviation
against the latitude or paleomagnetic latitude
the sampling site it's been known for a long
time that that increases with with latitude away
from the equator and it's fit reasonably well by
this model g simple two parameter model where a
is the um refers to the the vgp dispersion of the
equator and b um records the tendency of this
dispersion to increase with latitude so those
are the first two parameters and what we're after
misfit values of less than one so so we're in good
good shape there we've got maximum inclination
anomalies so that's a deviation of an inclination
from that expected from gad and that's very good
in line with observations for the last 10 million
years these are all taken from from cromwell 2018
we've got the vdm uh variance relative variance um
and this is also in line with what we extract
from uh from pint and it's only the only one
that marginally fails these five criteria is this
proportion transitional um one which is basically
saying that this simulation does not reverse
quite as often as uh we would expect it to um
for the given um reversal record for the last
10 million years okay so it's been kind of well
known for a while that if you increase the rating
but you drive a geodynamo simulation a bit harder
then that can increase the reversal frequency so
that's what we tried in this incidence in this
instance and we so a modest rayleigh number
increased from 1.6 1.8 times 10 to the 7
did indeed give us uh more reversals um as we
expected but it also had other detrimental effects
so this one is a worse one sort of misfit that's a
total misfit that's nearly doubled um we fixed the
proportion transitional that's now good um but
now we've got a higher model ga we've got more
vgp dispersion than we see in the record and our
variance in a relative variance of bdms normalized
failure intensities have also gone up out of out
of the range so this is fairly fairly typical
of what you see with these dyno simulations
you fix one thing and then you break others
okay but i also want to look at the what happened
to the overall bdm distribution as well because by
increasing the rayleigh number um for the second
simulation we also decreased quite substantially
on the 40 percent the the median bdm as well so we
made it rico made the distribution skewed to low
values okay um now this difference is a result of
increasing the rayleigh number so this is the sort
of signal that would be you know we're hoping um
to try and interpret from the paleomagnetic record
that the fields got weaker because something
has changed in the in the forcing perhaps due to
mental convection or so on and obviously you know
to get a nice distribution here we've got 5000
vdm so you don't need that many to be able to tell
that the the field has changed so approximately 60
would be sufficient to give you a 95 likelihood
of detecting this change and actually the global
distribution of where those vdms come from is
is not as critical as you might think it is um
what is really critical in telling and determining
whether or not you've had a real change in the vdm
distribution is the amount of time that you're
sampling okay so i'll show you that in a very
dramatic way from this second simulation so what
you might have noticed from these time series
what i call tilt and vdm here is that um
occasionally and most especially in this
time period here this simulation collapses into
a weak field state the vdm becomes much weaker
and the reversal rate goes through the roof it
becomes quite multipolar and that's illustrated
by this snapshot of the field here okay now if
we were to sample only this time period which is
we've taken a million years of model time
here so quite a substantial amount of time
and we'd end up with a bdm distribution
that gives you a medium that is 68 lower
than the actual value recorded so you
record a much more dramatic decrease
conversely if you went to the million years
subsequent to that you can see that that's the
time period where we've got unusual stability
for this simulation we're missing any of these
hyper reversing periods so then we get a
completely different distribution and we get
a 71 overestimate um and that's actually more
or less indistinguishable from what we saw in
the first simulation so then you would miss this
change um and the rayleigh number in this case and
the really crucial thing to notice here is that
if you're just basing the fact of whether you've
sampled sufficient time on the directions then
you'll end up in big trouble because of course
if you sample the full five million years of model
time then you end up with something very close to
gad which is good but if you sample any of these
other smaller shorter time intervals you also
end up with with mean vgps very close and within
errors of gaps so you would conclude that you had
a good time average from the directions but in
fact your intensity is is is poorly temporarily
representative okay so and just to bring
that back to earth um here's pad n2n it's
a model of dipole moment over the last
two million years and what we see is um
not quite as dramatic but still substantial
long-term changes so just if you simply just
look at the first million years compare it to the
second million year you've got a difference of 14
there which is which is significant and you could
obviously you know restrict yourself just to the
brooms and just to periods where you've got many
reversals and that that difference would grow
larger so i think the implications of this is that
yeah intensity time averages much more challenging
to observe than than directional time averages in
fact you know they may not even exist really in
any sense um and what that means is if they want
to see you want to detect changes in the dipole
moment um that you know we we can be reasonably
confident and not just a consequence of non-linear
geodynamic processes secular variations on um
then we really need a number of studies spanning
tens of millions of years ideally to be sure of
that okay so armed with that information um i
want to now turn uh briefly to uh the biggest and
thorniest question i guess the paleo intensities
to address in recent years one of those
uh which is the the question of when us
in accord did nucleate um so here there's been
progress in the theoretical side of things so um
chris davis and a bunch of other leads in
liverpool just published this this paper in ggi
um which essentially is saying that
independent of the the well at least with these
with multiple different thermal evolution models
so we've got one where the mental boundary heat
flow is diminishing exponentially through time
we've got one the dashed line where it's remaining
relatively constant both of these are associated
with red lines that show a very sharp peak at the
moment of inner core nucleation the red line is
the power available to drive the geodynamo so
inner core nucleation was a game changer in terms
of the power available to drive the geodynamo
and through a scaling law analysis which i don't
have time to do justice to here um it was shown
that we would expect such a increase in the power
available to drive the geodynamo to be evident
as a um as a large increase a sharp
increase in um in the dipole moment
okay so i guess the answer to the first answer
to this question when did a cynical nucleate
well it would be sometime after a sharp during at
the time of the sharp increase in dipole moment
okay so obviously been looking for this but for
some time now and this was uh one attempt in 2015
and that we published where we suggested that
it might be happening in the mesopotamia between
about a billion point five billion years ago more
recently because uh bonnaretal published this
paper suggesting that in fact it happened
considerably later than that during or soon
after the ediacaran period which terminated
540 million years ago so at this juncture i
will just give a shout out for a um for the pint
database which enables us to to improve on these
on these studies so this um has been newly updated
and just published online so a huge amount of work
from um from a lot of people here at liverpool
but note and notably um richard bonner and greg
patterson and richard's made this nice website as
well that's online now so you can download things
this is only presently up to date till the
end of 2019 there's a further update coming
on but most of the data that i'll just be
going over now um is subsequent to that um
yeah to to this update so it's not in this present
database but i'm totally what we're seeing okay so
i guess the first thing we're interested in is
was this this you know this result is this time
average of um at the set tills low vdm um from
the ediacaran uh published by bono atoll was that
supported by other data from a similar time period
uh so this was very much the phd of dan falmer
who's now at uh university of florida with
courtney sprain and a bunch of studies here
um kind of confirming this original finding
so we have the east european craton we've got
the grenville dykes and we've got skinner coat
lavas and they're all showing similar there's
a suggestion that there might be a bit of a
step change at the end which you know could
be indicative of interconnection i don't really
want to go there i guess the the main thing is
to to point out that the scale on the y-axis here
right so everything all these new data below 2
times 10 to the 22 meters squared so given
that today's field is uh around about eight and
the uh long term average over the last few hundred
million years is somewhere between four or five
these are really low estimates
consistently low estimates spanning
tens of millions of years it really does look
like the ediacaran was a period of sustained
low field for whatever reason
going back a bit earlier in time
method approach research is a bit of a wasteland
for sorry the neoprotectors are wasteland for um
for paleo intensity uh results have been trying
to fill that um and this is phd of simon lloyd
who's still with us at liverpool and he
published a study from franklin dykes
in the canadian arctic 720 million years and also
these bengal sills from northwestern australia
and these seem to support the trend shown here
by the dashed line of bono metal suggesting a
decay through this time but then there's a
wild card which is his mundane welt wells
spikes 750 million years uh also from northwest
australia and they're coming out relatively
uh high just 30 million years before the uh
the franklin dikes so you know this could be um
you know 30 million years that's time in the
final resort record for the big shift in dipole
moment or it could be simply the um the the
nonlinear geodynamic process that i referred to
um already um but either way it's looking quite
difficult and to be sure that we've got the
signature of the minicore nucleation uh happening
at the the ediacaran and looking a bit later in
time as well i'm sorry i keep on switching the the
time axis uh on you by the way but that's gonna
be your feet checks for the original uh
figures um but yeah a bit later in time
now we're looking at the mid um protozoa low and
um these are results from the phd louise hawkings
and um she established this um paper um proposing
mid paleozoic dipole low so this this period
um most of the the devonian and the um uh
early carboniferous where the fields again
seem to be sustained low very low values over
tens of millions of years and good quality
data um a bit later on we've got um not so
good quality data but strongly suggesting
that there's a sharp rise in in uh dipole
moment then around the cayenne on super crown
okay so you know variation like this typically
taken to to refer to mental uh force variations
uh rather than intercourse negation but we
don't know those two signals are overlapping
and put all that together uh final time axis
switch you can see there's all the new data in
red here you see the case for these um low dipole
moment periods in the ediacaran the midpoly zurich
and really highlighting that we need to address
the early paleozoic now we've got a few things
in motion 500 million years or so these tending to
come out quite low uh actually but we desperately
need something particularly from the um autovision
super crown to see if that was high um like we see
in the in the cayman so did we have a you know
a um an evolution like this or more like this
okay so um i've still got a little bit of time
left so i will move on to talking about the
um a little bit about actually how
we can use uh secular variation to um
rather than being a barrier to determining um deep
earth conditions how we can actually use it so
this is a study that we published a couple of
years ago um arguing that secular variation
was actually um a paleo secular variation very
powerful tool for telling us about the ancient
morphology of the field so this was based on
dynamo simulations first and foremost you can see
that as this model a parameter decreases as we go
along the section of these different dynamo models
then also the axial dipole dominance so this is
just the power in the axial dynamo axial dipole
um divided by the rest of the field truncated to
degree order 10 that goes up okay so and we can
see the earth using psv10 using um for the last 10
million years using ggf100k for the last hundred
thousand years that kind of sits somewhere in the
middle of this range when we put together a lot of
dynamo models and also included uh some various
models from earth including ggf100k those are
these green dots here and what we found was rather
a nice power law okay so the model g a parameter
could be used to predict this axial dipole
dominance okay and this was this struck as is very
um important because this model g is something
we can get billion years ago um whereas you know
the the shape of the magnetic field is not
so easy to estimate um before recent times
okay so this is just showing that many models
um like there are a few models were much more
stable like this blue one than today's field
uh some were a little bit more unstable
and this one and many were a lot more unstable
than what we see in the paleomagnetic records
okay so this is a combination compilation of psv
estimates vgp dispersion by latitude put together
from three recent studies in the last 300 million
years and then compared to a slightly older
study that looked at the pre-cambrian and the
extraordinary thing about these is that when you
fit the model g to them their parameters are very
very similar so when you average on these that's
not to say that secularisation never changes when
you look at it on these extremely long time scales
it looks very similar it doesn't look like
there's been any strong secular change in psv
okay and it's actually quite a narrower window
that we see so these these red dashed lines these
incorporate the error estimates from all three of
those composite curves that i just showed you and
you can see it's actually quite a narrow window
um within this power law so what this is saying
is that most dynamo simulations are
falling outside the region most of them are
just too uh too unstable and um not
nipper not axial dipole dominated enough
okay and the stability of the shape of the
magnetic field over billions of years is
you know it's not a new idea it's something that's
kind of relied on for tectonic reconstructions
paleo geography and so on so i'm just showing here
a reference to to dave evans paper from 2006 where
he used evaporites to argue that gad was a pretty
good assumption all the way back to our keyan
times and we've got this quotation from here
that consistently axial and dipole geomagnetic
reference time and implies stability of geodynamic
processes on billion year time scales all right
now that's true and that is actually quite
surprising and quite important what was telling us
that the magnetic field has been so stable and the
thing that makes it even more surprising is that
these geodynamo simulations are really not stable
right so i said already that most of them are too
variable okay and i've got this this kind of
golden window shown here but now we're plotting
model ga parameter against the rayleigh number
okay and what you can see is that there's a very
clear pattern this isn't whether you're chemically
forced or thermally forced whether you have
homogeneous boundary conditions or heterogeneous
boundary conditions with these parameters what you
see is that you increase the radial number
you move quite quickly through this region
of stability and into into fields that don't look
like the long-term average okay now given that the
earth has been subject to all sorts of forcings
from various things not released in cornucleation
uh over its history it's quite surprising
then that we can still maintain ourselves in
this field so just wanted to highlight them these
these new models have just been run um by uh john
mound and chris davies at leeds and they gave
us the gas coefficient to play around with and
saw is that one of these one with homogeneous
boundary conditions should say that these are
run this e is the ekman number so this is the
viscous over the rotation force this one's an
order of magnitude lower than the rest it's it's
closer to um to earth-like parameters which are
which are far beneath there's something like
10-16 um but argue to be in the same regime
where rotation is dominant or is a is an important
force in ordering the flow within the core
but also sufficiently high railing number that
you get a lot of turbulence as well when you run
these simulations if you have homogeneous boundary
conditions then you get a similar result to the
rest you're very quickly going into the multipolar
regime well away from the the earth-like
observations okay but a little bit of um
actually quite a lot of um heterogeneous thermal
heterogeneity at the base of the mantle that seems
to have this remarkably remarkable stabilizing
effect so the pattern of heterogeneities that was
taken from um from seismic uh tomography of the
lower base mantle for masters at all uh q star
is the magnitude of this of this heterogeneity
we can see what's happening here unlike in any
of the other cases we've got a factor of three
increase in the rating number um but we still
have a stable model ga parameter and a stable um
dipole-dominated field so this may be significant
so just to briefly talk about how that can be um
so essentially this is the the flow in in
two of these models and what you can see
is there's big sort of faded patches
in the middle representing the shapes
of the llsbps we're just below the
coromantic boundary here about 200 kilometers
and um we see the flow has been suppressed very
heavily and by the the llsvps these are hot
they don't suck the heat flux underneath them
is very very low and so they are suppressing
the flow in the core beneath them and also the
magnetic fields at the core mental boundary is
therefore heavily um governed particularly at
low latitudes by these regions of suppressed
flow so essentially we have very little
um magnetic flux generated essentially the
field's imposing an order on um uh sorry the
the lsvp's are imposing a large scale order on
the field particularly at low latitudes which
sends suppressions like the equatorial dipole
which would upset the um the dipole dominant
the axial dipole dominance of the field
okay and just very quickly to say
we also see longitudinal variations
uh in these simulations so they vary from model to
model but the final one of these looks very much
like the variability that we see in um in ggf
100 k as well so we've got marginal suppression
of vgp angular dispersion um above where the vgp
where the yellow sdps are okay i'll skip over this
and yeah just make a final final point that this
these green points these are the ones that they um
that sit nicely in the window that
are from these uh heterogeneous
um low echelon number simulations that feature
these this regional stratification and so the
red circle in here is ggf100k so that also sits
nicely in the in the middle of this and the fact
that this is so stable does it suggest that a
lot of our svps are stabilizing the magnetic
fields could they be doing so over geological time
scales um well i just want to point out here that
i'm not saying that these lsvps look exactly the
same over billions of years um but you know if
we've got a simulation like this one geodynamic
mental flow over the last 300 million years
you can see that the lsvps represented by these
areas of low coronal heat flow have moved around
in blue so they've moved around a lot over this
time but they're still covering significant
amounts of the of the low um of the equatorial
parts of the common boundary that might be
sufficient to impose this large scale order and
stabilizing effect on the magnetic field okay so
summary of findings um i guess i've just about
stuck to time um there but you can read these
for yourself and i'll take any questions thank you
thank you andy let's give a big round of applause
thank you very much uh very interesting talk
um and the floor now is open for questions
you can use the chat the chat box or ask
them away yes cathy go ahead thank you
okay sorry having trouble meeting there no problem
point of clarification please um i think i'm maybe
i misunderstood this but early on you said that
uh when you were talking about the formation of
the inner core um did i understand you correctly
to say that the increase in power that you get
from the formation of the inner core necessarily
results in an increase in dipole moment
well that's what the scaling law predicts okay so
there's a nice gaming law based on the qg mac um
force balance which is thought to be appropriate
for earth and hundreds of dynamo simulations
that that chris collated and found yeah a um a
nice scaling law um that predicted that outcome
one thing to be to be born in mind with that is
that all those simulations were dipole dominated
okay so what that um means is actually if that
power tricks it over towards the multipolar um uh
behavior then actually you might expect the
opposite but yes as things stand with the um uh
yeah with the current state of the art of
dynamo simulations and then the scaling law that
applies um from that it does seem as though uh
yes we should expect a significant increase in
back online as a result thank you
thank you er johannes yeah thank
you hi andy thanks for the nice talk
thank you now i have first first a remark and then
a question i guess because to kathy's um question
i mean for the scaling you just use the scaling
laws right based on dynamo simulations but also
some theory which basically tell you that the
energy or the magnetic field strength goes with
the power to the one-third right so so that's what
all it tells you but i think this is not really
based on simulations that have no inner core
and something that have a core and when you do
this you see that basically the increased medical
field strength that you could see as an observer
is much weaker and this scaling node would predict
simply because when you nucleate an inner core
the action of dynamic generation moves deeper
into the core so what you see at the surface is
somewhat less than the power law predict but this
was not my question so my question regards these
simulations you showed at the end these slow
ecma numbers 10 to minus 5 simulations right
which looked quite nice actually and had this uh
tomographic heat flux at the cone metal boundary
so are these simulations also reversing or are
they not reversing no they're not reversing
they're so they're computationally
expensive as you can imagine and so
100 000 years of model time so half a diffusion
time okay but when you look at the wikipedis
person it looks about the correct amount yes which
might suggest that they could reverse okay so the
final slide that i didn't have time to show you
is actually comparing them to to ggf 100k because
that's also obviously 100 000 years that doesn't
reverse either the le champ does not register as a
reversal according to these criteria so therefore
they actually um yeah ggf 100k fails the criteria
doesn't perform particularly well um and these
simulations much better ggf100k than they do the
10 million year simulations and that could be just
because yeah they're not running long enough for
the for reversals happen because that
will then indeed knock on impact on the um
uh on the bdm variability as well very strongly
um yeah so that would be another criteria that's
kind of automatically missed just by them
being too short to have reversals thank you
thank you any other question
maybe you can show us the slide you've prepared
with the g gfk 100k a model i'm curious now yeah
uh okay so i'll just keep this so first of
all i show you comparison to the uh the last
10 million years um so here it's shown graphically
rather than as a table but for the four different
models sorry i can't see it sorry oh sorry sorry
sorry thank you a lot of questions coming now
that's good thank you okay okay i'll keep this
brief but yeah so this is it for for um for the
qpm criteria shown as a green bar so you can see
that for model ga and the inclination normally
which is kind of the morphological one that
they do pretty well but then model g b not so
good and then the bdm variability and reversals
yeah not good at all um but then that's also
bring on the red bar to show what ggf-100k is
like that has the same problem so essentially
um yeah it's uh model g b is is it's very flat
it's ggf 100k which is kind of interesting i'm
not sure what that signifies but it also has way
too low bdm variability um and yeah no reverses
thank you so uh i will take now carl's
question yeah hi andy thank you very
very nice talk um i was especially also
interested in these very low ecma number
models because uh they seem to show that you get
a much finer structure in the heat flow but also
probably in the general convection patterns in
the outer core and as we know the ecma number
for the earth is even i think seven orders of
magnitudes smaller than what you showed so so we
probably have to expect that this fine structure
is by far finer even than these models so uh
would you say that the reason for the fact that
the mental illness also commented boundary in
homogeneities become more important is that
the frequency or the wavelength of the of the
convection patterns is becomes much
smaller than the wavelength of the uh
of the inhomogeneities at the core mental boundary
is that the reason why why this dominates or it
could well be so yes i think that's that that
makes um yeah good sense so essentially um it's
yeah the so these models show exhibit this
phenomenon of regional inversion lenses you know
which which um mound that are published in 2019
nature geoscience but in non-magnetic simulations
okay so it's essentially regional stratification
of the uppermost core so and what that is is
yeah the so and that was robust over you know very
large parameter range providing yeah you were at
these uh you know these low ecma numbers and yes
the reason is essentially that as i understand it
um is that you need to be in a regime where
the mental large-scale mental in homogeneities
set up um a lens of stratified flow or
suppressed flow at least and then as you
increase the rayleigh number although you know the
the flow gets faster it also becomes finer scale
and therefore yes it just can't it can't disrupt
something that's so so much bigger than it is
and yeah the the the lower ecma numbers
sorry the higher ecma numbers if you're
at two higher numbers then yeah you just
the these homogeneities just do completely
different things you don't you don't seem to get
this this regional stratification at all either
you stratify everything um or you end up or
you yeah and to very great depths in the core
sometimes or you um yeah you just you don't
really you have sort of ephemeral effects
thank you thank you um andrei
thank you andy great talk very clear very
clear cut i have a very brief question
actually concerning the data you showed
well uh what would you think of the this huge
dispersion vdm dispersion during the camera
and also it seems that there there have not
been some so many recent studies of this period
i fully agree and i would love yeah to see more
so any idea why the dispersion could be so high
if it's real if it's real or it's just the data
i i i mean the data quality yeah i
mean yeah that's another period to look
yes it is i don't know i don't want
to comment really on whether okay
it could be the the quality of the
data that's i mean some of the studies
are universally high and that kind of you know
that could fit with some of the dynamic stations
where you where you enter this you know it tends
to be low railing numbers you get a very efficient
you know um dipole dominated uh behavior
where the field doesn't you know never
really collapses so you end up with quite a
small dispersion but then yeah if um quickly
it always has been a temptation to tell okay
you have super crown you have high vdm high and
because i think you know i think you can a
super con is just a time where you haven't
quite edged over into the reversing you know
regime that collapse and i think that that
can be quite a subtle transition to that you
know so you know i've heard the argue that
maybe the brooms could be like a super con
and you know i don't see anything to either
thank you well another thing probably not
only the quality of the data but also the
the uncertainty in the age they usually
eye for for all the times we're talking
variability they're real or but on which age
range sorry i commented um thank you uh gunther
hi andy nice effort in putting this talk
together like you did for this presentation
i i i admit i don't really understand the dynamo
and how it works and i always have this uh how
how how what's the what's the role of coriolis
force when you are generating these dynamos
uh okay so i guess i have to be quite careful
there's people that are infinitely better
qualified than i am to talk about those actual
dynamic modelers um but as i mean rotation is
is absolutely paramount as a force in the dynamo
we think so it organizes um the flow parallel to
the rotation axis so it adds kind of almost a
rigidity um to the flow structure so it stops
it all just got kind of a radial convection and
instead forms these you know tends to form these
these columns that are aligned um with the
rotation axis so but it's it's you know it's
as paramount in the force balance on so on so they
would be going let's say in clockwise direction in
the northern hemisphere and counterclockwise
in the southern hemisphere correct
yes as far as i understand
it janice do you want to
oh you have you have this well
we tend to think of these columns
right and they go through north-south right
they go just right through the earth core
and you have both types you know counter rotating
and clockwise and counter-clockwise rotation both
columns exist but they are ordered there so there
are columns along the rotation axis as any set but
both types exist i mean i think of it as like
i guess the um meteorology sound so you get
you get depressions and and you get cycling and
cycling yeah that's that's a similar origin right
but i mean these columns they you see them
in in in simple simulations of course when it
becomes more complex like these eggman number
ten to minus five simulations and you showed
you don't really see columns anymore or or only
you know hints of it and in a statistical sense
you don't see big columns reaching through
from north to south that's not possible
anymore because everything is so turbulent
but in a statistical sense this is still there
okay and so now it comes to my question
so it looks to me that in order that once you
have a certain rotation rate that these columns
are forming but there must be a certain rate
which probably relates to the viscosity i don't
know at which you perturb this column formation
and i wonder i mean what i all thought about
estimate estimation of this rotation rate which
would become critical uh for these columns so
my my understanding is that rotation rate is very
very much less than the rotation rate of the earth
so we are very much into the rotationally
dominated or rotationally influenced regime
so for example venus would not have that or would
it no i think venus as far as i understand i think
the problem with venus is not the rotation rate
i know that it's much slower um but it's still
sufficient to um you know to to allow for a you
know for a rotationally dominated dynamo it's
just that um yeah probably the heat flow is not
enough on venus so that's probably what it was
well thank you andy hey thank you um boris
hello hello andy thank you for your thank you for
your presentation i i have a question about the
the influence of the lls vps on the magnetic
field and um i was wondering what kind of uh
influence it has
do do you think that the llsvps would produce
a different magnetic field whether you are
over the lls vps or 90 degrees or for what kind
of um what would be the influence yes of the
lsvps on the geometry of the magnetic i assume
there's field lot of work to be done in that
regard um but what we see in these ones is that
yeah they suppress the magnetic field directly
beneath them um and then obviously you
know that's at the core model boundary
then you go all the way up to the surface
and you smooth that out quite a bit so it's
but it's perhaps um observable the surface you
know ggf100k you know seems to seems to show this
you know this nice non-zonal signature
of um suppressed vgp dispersion above
those those lsdps so if you move them if you move
the lsvps around you might expect that signature
to go around i guess what what is really wide
open at the moment is what that does to the
sort of you know the next uh stage of the the
global field or the you know the the axisometric
field whether they were still if you just had one
big lsvp at the equator whether that would still
um impose a similar stabilizing effect to that
which we see at two i suspect it would have a
qualitatively similar effect um just because it's
going to impose a large scale order on the field
it's going to not allow you know the actual
the equatorial dipole is the main you know
disruptive influence to the axial dipole
and you know if you can't have that if you
don't if you've got you know quite a strong zonal
asymmetry sorry non-zonal symmetry on the equator
okay thank you and how i have a second question
related to this is um how would you have your
equatorial dipole in how the equatorial dipole
would be positioned with respect to this uh
lls vp uh geometry do you know this or oh yeah i
think are you getting at the sort of persistent
equatorial dipole idea for the yeah maybe or or
maybe the magnetic field could still be dominated
by an actual dipole but i guess you could
have a combination of the two or i don't know
yeah so i don't know this is real speculation
so i just don't know but i guess you know if if
you didn't have lsvps at the equator at all then
maybe that would help an equatorial dipole for me
and then it might be rooted you know to perhaps
regions of particularly high heat flow okay
okay okay thank you very much thank you thank
you all unfortunately the time is nearly up
so uh we don't have a time for more
questions um thanks again andy another
big round of applause for you thank you very much
let me share my screen for our next uh updates
um so the the seminar schedule so far looks like
we are gonna have marco mafione from university of
birmingham um the 16th of march and then 23rd of
march we're gonna have uh uh two two speakers from
the royal academy of art in the act and and maybe
in april or maybe after the eg we're gonna move to
eu eastern hemisphere time slot and we always
welcome more speakers and then thank you very
much again for coming and i would like to remind
you that you can watch and rewatch the videos
on the youtube channel and yeah i hope to see
you next time thank you very much thank you all